Guide to the Caroline Sheridan Norton Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Caroline Sheridan Norton collection
1830-1876
GEN MSS 260
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1
(4 boxes)
The collection contains letters and writings by or about Caroline Sheridan Norton. The letters are to recipients such as Robert Browning, Henry Cholmondeley-Pennell, Mrs. Catherine Gore, Nathaniel Ogle, Lady Anna Stirling Maxwell, and Frances Trollope, as well as a letter to William Francis Cowper-Temple concerning the death of his uncle, Lord Melbourne. Writings include several autograph poems, and the autograph manuscript of "Love in the World," a novel written when Norton was a young girl.
Norton, Caroline Sheridan, 1808-1877
Slade, Bertha Coolidge, 1880-1953
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Caroline Sheridan Norton, 1808-1877
Caroline Sheridan Norton was a British feminist, social reformer, and author.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains letters and writings by or about Caroline Sheridan Norton. The letters are to recipients such as Robert Browning, Henry Cholmondeley-Pennell, Mrs. Catherine Gore, Nathaniel Ogle, Lady Anna Stirling Maxwell, and Frances Trollope, as well as a letter to William Francis Cowper-Temple concerning the death of his uncle, Lord Melbourne. Writings include several autograph poems, and the autograph manuscript of "Love in the World," a novel written when Norton was a young girl.
Accompanying the collection is a typescript of Bertha Coolidge Slade's undated essay "Some Unrecorded Letters of Caroline Norton in the Altschul Collection of the Yale University Library."
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Frank Altschul Gift, 1839-1876. II. Bertha Coolidge Slade Gift, 1840-1865. III. Other Papers, 1830-1874.
Authors, English -- Archives; British literature -- 19th century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Cholmondeley-Pennell, H. (Henry), 1837-1915; Gore, Mrs. (Catherine Grace Frances), 1799-1861; Melbourne, William Lamb, Viscount, 1779-1848; Mount-Temple, William Francis Cowper-Temple, Baron, 1811-1888; Norton, Caroline Sheridan, 1808-1877; Ogle, Nathaniel; Slade, Bertha Coolidge, 1880-1953; Stirling Maxwell, Anna, -1874; Trollope, Frances Milton, 1780-1863
- Frank Altschul Gift, 1839-1876; Series I
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Correspondence, and Writings.
  Scope and Contents
  Gift of Frank Altschul, 1937-1958.
  - Correspondence
    - ALS to Robert Browning, London, 1876 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      With typescript
    - AL in third person to Messrs. Chapman & Hall, London, 1851 Jan (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 2 ALS to Lord Conyngham [Albert Denison, 1st Baron Londesborough], Frampton, Dorchester; London, [1840], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 4 ALS to Mrs. William Francis Cowper-Temple, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS to William Francis Cowper-Temple, [London], [1848] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Concerning the death of Lord Melbourne
    - 2 ALS to William Francis Cowper-Temple, Airtrey, Scotland, 1872, [1875] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 3 ALS to Mr. Foublanque, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS to Lt. Gore-Jones, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ALS to Dr. Edward Craven Hawtrey, Richmond, England, [1840?] May 18 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS to Edward Hopkins, 1850 Jun 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS to Richard Henry Horne, London, 1844 Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - ALS to Charles Henry Bellenden Ker, [Lisbon], [1848] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - ALS to "Dearest Kitty", [1866?] (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Paper watermarked 1866
    - ANS to James Philip Lacaita, [1848?] Nov 12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 6 ALS to Charles Locock, [1846-1863?] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - ALS to Daniel Maclise, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALS to "Moppy," Netherby, Carlisle, [1860?] (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Mentioning Ian Campbell's book of Gaelic studies
    - 14 ALS and 1 AL to Nathaniel Ogle, [1839-1844?] (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Enclosures: T. H. Talfand's AL (copy) to Lord Lyndhurst; Ogle's notes on the Infant Custody Bill, and what appears to be his notes on Mrs. Norton's trial
    - ANS to Anthony Panizzi, London, circa 1845 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - AL, signed with initials to "Presumptuous Scot," Stover House, [1856?] (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - ALS to Henry Reeve, Netherby, Carlisle, [1847] Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - ALS to Mrs. Henry Reeve, [1866?] (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - ALS to Mrs. Henry Reeve, [1867?] (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Paper watermarked 1860
    - ALS to [Alexis Francois] Rio, [London], undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - ALS to Mrs. John Edward Sartoris, [1857] (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Paper watermarked 1857
    - ALS to Dr. Sedgwick, Sorrento, Italy, [1876?] (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - ALS to Lady Anna Stirling Maxwell, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - ANS to General Vulp, London, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 8 ALS to unidentified recipients, 1840-1873, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Letter of 1873 concerns Sara Coleridge
    - Photocopy of a letter to an unidentified recipient, Friday, Sep 8, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Writings
    - "The Child of the Islands," autograph manuscript poem, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - "An Entomological Postscript to a Botanical Specimen," photocopy of a poem in an unidentified hand, accompanied by a picture of the bread fruit tree, undated
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 108
    - "From Moore," photocopy of an autograph manuscript poem dated 1835 Dec 22, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "The Mother," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "On Mr. C. Sheridan saying he feared Mrs. Stanhope," photocopy of autograph manuscript poem dated 1835 Dec 24, undated
      See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 109
    - Photocopy of a title-page of "A Plain Letter to the Lord Chancellor...By Pearce Stevenson, Esq.," with signature of Mrs. Norton, and part of a note in her hand concerning the pseudonym, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - "The Question," photocopy of an autograph manuscript poem, undated
      See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 110
    - "To the Sun, at Lisbon, 1849," autograph manuscript poem, signed (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Bertha Coolidge Slade Gift, 1840-1865; Series II
  Gift of Bertha Coolidge Slade, 1938-1940.
  - Green volume labeled: Caroline Norton Original Manuscripts and Letters. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    General note
    Contents analyzed below, in order of appearance in volume.
    - Pen and ink sketch of a female figure riding a broom, signed and dated, 1847
    - "The Poet's Inkstand": autograph manuscript poem, undated
      Manuscript note verso, "I have your letter, dear, since I wrote"
    - ALS (in French) to Mme. Richard?, London, Feb 6
    - AL to "Marie", undated
      With pen and ink sketch
    - ALS to Mrs. Symons, London, [1846?] Apr 8
    - ALS to [Henry?] Taylor, London, undated
    - ALS to [John Doran?], Newton Abbott, Devon, undated
    - AL, signed with initials, to Mrs. Edmund Phipps, undated
      Illustrated with pen and ink drawings
    - AL, signed with initials, to Brinsley Homan, Frampton, Dorchester, 1840 Apr 23
    - AL, signed with initials, to "Brinn", undated
    - ALS to William Cox Bennett, London, 1861 Feb 11
    - ALS to William Chappell, undated
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, undated
    - ALS to Mrs. [Samuel Carter?] Hall, undated
    - ALS to William Charles Macready, London, undated
    - ALS to James Howard, London, undated
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, undated
    - AL, signed with initials, to [Alexander Duff-Gordon], undated
    - ALS to Thomas Crofton Croker, London, undated
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, London, undated
    - ALS to Mrs. [Samuel Carter?] Hall, London, undated
    - 3 ALS to Henry Cholmondeley Pennell, London, [1865?]
    - ALS to Richard Bentley, undated
    - ALS to "Dear Bird," London, 1863
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, fragment, undated
  - ALS to Mr. Combe [?], 1843 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Concerning the "Case of Joshua Hardy"
  - ALS to [whom it may concern], Hampton Court, Dorchester (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Recommending John Payte for a position
  - Slade, Bertha Coolidge. Typed copy of her essay, "Some Unrecorded Letters of Caroline Norton in the Altschul Collection of the Yale University Library", undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Other Papers, 1830-1874; Series III
  Organized into two subseries: Correspondence, and Writings
  The series contains additional materials acquired from various sources between 1942 and 1986.
  - Correspondence
    - ALS to James Alexander, Kirkaldy, N.B., 1872 Nov 11 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      Purchase, 1969
    - ALS to Sir Augustus, Apr 10 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Purchase, 1974
    - ALS to [Mr. Bareley?], undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - ALS to Mr. Barnes, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Purchase, 1960
    - ALS to Lord Belfast, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
      About music
      Purchase, 1966
    - ALS to Dear Bird, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
      Purchase, 1942
    - ALS to Henry George Bohn, London, 1871 Nov 28 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - ALS to Miss Byrne, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
      Gift, 1962
    - ALS to Messrs. Chapman & Hall, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - ALS to Lady Chatterton, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
      Gift, 1953
    - ALS to "Lord Clarence," Mayfair, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
      With 2 autograph notes from Lord Clarence and "The Duke" added
    - ALS to Lady Clifford, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - ALS to [R. Colburn], Bolton St, [1840 Oct 26] (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - ALS to G. Conant at the Marlborough Police Office, Framington, Dorchester, Nov 16 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Purchase, 1968
    - ALS to Mrs. Cowper, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
      Purchase, 1967
    - ALS to T. Dantis [?], London, May 7 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      Concerns Stuart of Dunleath
      Purchase, 1971
    - 2 ALS to Miss Dempster, 1867, [1869?] (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - 2 ALS to Mlle. D'Henin, [Greenwich?]; London, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
      Accompanied by a fragment of a letter to an unidentified recipient containing a small pen sketch labeled (in another hand) "The effects of a gale at Boulogne"
      Purchase, 1944
    - ALS to Father Ellice, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - ALS to [Fisher, Son & Co.], London, [1846-1849] (Box 2, Folder 59)
      About Fisher's drawing-room scrapbooks, edited by Mrs. Norton
      Purchase, 1983
    - 10 ALS to Mrs. Catherine Gore, Frampton Park, 1836, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - ALS to Lt. Gore-Jones, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - ALS to Grote, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
      Purchase, 1986
    - ALS to Dr. Hawtrey, circa 1845 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - ALS to "My Good Henchman", undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - 4 ALS to Henrietta, Frampton Court, 1860-1874 (Box 2, Folder 65)
      Last on page 2-4 of a note written by an unidentified granddaughter
      Purchase, 1965
    - ALS to Mrs. Hort, Keir near Dunblace, N.B., undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - ALS to Mrs. Hughes, Jun 12 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - ALS to Mr. Jesse, Nov 16 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      Purchase, 1970
    - ALS to William Lefanu, Keir, [1874?] Nov 30 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - ALS to "Dear Mary," Southampton, 1843 Sep-Oct (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - ALS to John Murray, London, Mar 10 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - ALS to Miss Peard, Torquay, 1874 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - 2 ALS to Henry Cholmondeley-Pennell, Dorchester, [1865?] (Box 2, Folder 73)
      Purchase, 1942 and 1944
    - ALS to Miss Philp, 1870 Oct 15 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - ALS to Mrs. Reid, Jun 1 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Envelope to Madame Richard, undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - 4 ALS to Mr. [John Edward] Sartoris, undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - AN, invitation to Mr. Sheet in the third person, Mayfair, Apr 14 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - AL, signed with initials, to Mrs. Shelley, 1837 Mar 22 (Box 2, Folder 79)
      Purchase, 1946
    - ALS to her mother, Caroline Henrietta Callander Sheridan, [1850-1851] (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - ALS to Mrs. Sinclair, [London], undated (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - AL in third person to Mr. Smethurst [?], London, [1877 Mar 3] (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - ALS to "Soft-Eyes", May 27 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - ALS to Richard Stephens, Brighton, Apr 16 (Box 2, Folder 84)
      Returning his son's "roll" of poetry and criticizing the same.
    - ALS to Mrs. Stirling, Mar 2 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - ALS to Mr. Taylor, Mayfair, 1857 Jan 19 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - ALS and postal cover to Mr. Tom Taylor, London, [1852] Nov 15 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - ALS to Annie Young, undated (Box 2, Folder 88)
      Gift, 1977
    - 11 ALS to unidentified recipients, [1830]-1853, undated (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - ALS to "Sir", 1840 Jun 11 (Box 2, Folder 90)
      Sending "a vol: of Poems I have just published" with the hope that "if they should seem to you to deserve a good word of favourable opinion - you would be rendering me an essential service at this time"
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, [1840] (Box 2, Folder 91)
      "I enclose the signature for the portrait... "
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, [1862] Feb 8 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - ALS to an unidentified stained-glass window manufacturer, Scotland, 1870 Feb 6 (Box 2, Folder 93)
      With fragment of an ALS concerning lady pianists Purchase, 1986
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, Maiden Bradley, Jan 3 (Box 2, Folder 94)
      Purchase, 1972
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, [London], Jan 12 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, London, Mar 29 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - ALS to Frances Trollope, [1832] Aug 16 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      Purchase, 1973
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, undated (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, Frampton, Dorchester, undated (Box 2, Folder 99)
      About "The Abbess of Minister" Purchase, 1983
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, undated (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - AN to an unidentified recipient, undated (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Writings and Other Papers
    - "In the Storm": AMs poem, signed, undated (Box 2, Folder 102)
      Wrapper addressed to the editor of The Scotsman
    - "Love in 'The World'": autograph manuscript of a novel, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 103)
      Endorsed by Mrs. Norton: "Prosy, foolish little book written partly as a girl." Fragmentary drafts of verses are written on end papers
      Purchase, 1957
      See also: Volumes, Box 3, folder 107
    - Untitled poem, beginning "Like one who knows that he has wooed in vain" (with fragment of a poem on reverse crossed out) autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Untitled poem, beginning "Truth! no more of women-": autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Photograph of Caroline Sheridan Norton, undated (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - "Love in 'The World'": autograph manuscript of a novel, 1830 (Box 3, Folder 107)
- Oversize, undated
  - "An Entomological Postscript to a Botanical Specimen," poem in an unidentified hand, accompanied by a picture of the bread fruit tree, undated (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - "On Mr. C. Sheridan saying he feared Mrs. Stanhope", 1835 Dec 24 (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - "The Question", undated (Box 4, Folder 110)